in the final part of today's lecture
저는 오늘 강의의 마지막 부분에서
i want to talk a little bit about some
우리가 흥미로운 의사 결정과 문제 해결을
more advanced materials
하기위해 모방학습을
about some other ways that we can use
사용 할 수있는 몇 가지 다른 방법들에
imitation learning to solve interesting
대한 더 나아간 자료들에 대해
decision making and control problems
이야기를 하고 싶습니다.
so this other imitation idea that i'm
그래서 제가 말하고자 하는
going to talk about
이 다른 모방 아이디어는
deals with how data that is
한 가지 작업에 대해
not necessarily optimal for one task
최적이 아닌 데이터가 다른 작업에
could be optimal for another one and how
최적이 될 수 있는지에 대한 것 과,
we can leverage that observation
우리가 어떻게 그 관찰을
for imitation learning so let's say that
모방 학습에 활용할 수 있는지를 의미합니다.
you have a trajectory for your agent
여러분의 에이전트의 궤적이
that reached some point p1
p1에 도달했다고 가정해봅시다.
right so if you have many trajectories
만약 여러분이 p1에 도달하는 궤적을
that all reach p1 that's good you can
많이 가지고 있다면, 여러분은 제한된 학습의
use those trajectories of limitation
궤적을 사용할 수 있고 p1에
learning and learn how to reach p1
도달하는 방법을 배울 수 있습니다.
but what if you have a bunch of
그러나 하나는 p1에 도달하고
demonstrations that all reach
다른 하나는 p2에 도달하고
different points one of them reached p1
또 다른 하나는 p3에 도달하는
another one reached p2 another one
각기 다른 지점에 도달하는
reached p3
다양한 선지를 가지고 있다면
now the trouble is that you might not
지금 당신이 겪고 있는 문제는
have enough demonstrations
다양한 포인트중 하나에 대한
for any one of those points by itself so
데모가 충분하지 않다는것일지도 모릅니다
maybe if you just use the demonstrations
만약 당신이 p1에 대한
for p1
데모를 사용한다면
you won't actually be able to learn to
실질적으로 p1에 성공적으로
reach p1 successfully
도달하는것을 배우기 힘들것입니다.
what if you condition your policy on the
지금 도달한 기점을 기준으로
point that was reached
정책(policy)를 조건화하면 어떨까요?
now even if you have just a single
각 점에 대해서 하나의 시연만
demonstration for each point
가지고 있다고 해도말입니다
you can learn a conditional policy kind
당신은 단지 p를
of amounts to just appending p to the
상태에 추가하기 위한
and that conditional policy would then
조건부 정책 종류를 배울 수 있습니다.
be able to reach any point
그리고 이러한 방법으로 추가정보에
including p1 so in this way by
당신의 정책(policy)를 조건화 함으로써
conditioning your policy on additional
그 조건부 정책은 p1을 나타내는
information
어떤 지점에 도달할 수 있을 것입니다
you can actually train policies for
실제로 해당 작업에 대한 데이터가
performing some tasks even if you didn't
충분하지 않더라도 일부작업을
have enough data for that task
수행하기 위한 정책(policy)를 교육할 수 있습니다
there are a number of works that have
이 아이디어를 한 가지 혹은 다른형태로
used this idea in one form or another
사용한 많은 작품들이 있습니다.
that i want to tell you about briefly
우리는 이 목표 조건을
so we're going to call this goal
행동 복제라고 부를 것입니다
condition behavior cloning and during
그리고 훈련하는 동안 우리는
training we'll observe
일반적으로 모든 다른 것들을 하는
a bunch of demonstrations that in
많은 시연들을 관찰할 것입니다.
but then we're going to treat each
성공적인 사례로 취급할 것입니다.
demonstration as a successful example
그 데모가 실제로 성공한 것이
for doing whatever it is that that
무엇이든 간에 말입니다
demonstration actually succeeded at
이러한 내용들이 제가 간단히 말씀드리고자 하는내용입니다.
so if the demonstration reached the
그래서 만약 해당 데모가 s_t에 도달 했다면
state st it's a successful demonstration
그것은 's_t'에 도달하기 위한 성공적인 시연이고,
for reaching st and then we'll learn a
조건부 상태 정책 및 조건상태를
conditional state and condition on goal
목표에 따라 배울 것입니다.
so the way that this works that for each
그래서 이것이 작동하는 방식은
demo you basically select the goal to be
각각의 데모에서 기본적으로 도달한
the last state that was reached
마지막 목표를 선택한 다음
and then just do regular behavior
규칙적인 행동을 복제하는 것이고,
this idea has been used in a few papers
이러한 아이디어는 몇몇 논문에 사용되어 왔습니다.
here are a couple of examples i'm going
여기에는 몇 가지 예시들이 있습니다.
to actually talk about the first one
제가 처음으로 말하고자 하는 것은
called learning latent plants from play
'latent plants'라 불리는 것을 놀이로 부터 배우는것입니다.
and the idea in this paper was to
그리고 이 논문에서 아이디어는
collect data from
특별히 아무것도 하지 않는
human demonstrators that are not doing
인간 표본으로부터
anything in particular
데이터를 수집하는 것이었습니다.
but are actually just
하지만 실제로는
attempting a wide range of different
다양한 행동들을 시도하고 있습니다.
essentially select the last state as a goal
마지막 상태를 목표로 선택하도록 처리됩니다.
the actual model architecture in this
이 논문의 실제 모델
paper is a little bit complicated
아키텍처는
for the reasons that i described
앞서 설명한 이유들로 인해
earlier in the lecture essentially
약간 복잡합니다.
in order for this to work
이것이 작동하기 위해서는
the imitation needs to be very powerful
모방이 매우 강력할 필요가 있습니다
it needs to match the expert very
즉, 전문가와 매우 정확하게
accurately
일치시킬 필요가 있습니다.
which means it has to deal with
이것은 그것이 다중 모드와 non-markovian에 대한
multimodality and non-markovian problems
문제를 다루어야 한다는 것을 의미합니다.
the way that it does this is actually by
이것이 하는 방법은
using a combination of autoregressive
실제로 자기 회귀 이산화와
discretization
잠재 변수 모델의
and a latent variable model so if you
조합을 사용하는 것입니다.
remember in a latent variable model
만약 당신이 잠재 변수 모델에서
we feed an additional noise input into
기억한다면 우리는 정책에 추가 노이즈를 입력을 공급하고
and that noise input allows us to
그 노이즈 입력은 우리가 임의의 출력 분포를
represent arbitrary output distributions
나타낼 수 있도록 합니다.
so it's kind of a more sophisticated
즉 그것은 조금더 정교해진
imitation learning architecture
모방학습 아키텍처입니다.
but the overall algorithm follows the
그러나 전체적인 알고리즘은
scheme that i had on the previous slide
이전 슬라이드에서 제가 가지고 있던 방식을 따릅니다.
and once this policy is trained it can
그리고 이 정책이 훈련되면 그것은 실제로
actually reach a variety of different
다양한 다른 목표에 도달할 수 있습니다.
so here the image on the left shows the
여기 왼쪽에 있는 이미지는
goal and the video on the right shows
목표와 비디오를 보여줍니다.
the policy actually trying to reach that
오른쪽에 있는 이미지는
goal and this is a single policy
실제로 그 목표에 도달하는 도달하려는 정책을 보여줍니다
trained on a wide variety of different
그리고 이것은 다양한 다른 훈련 데이터에 훈련되는 당일 정책입니다
now another idea that we could imagine
이 결과를 보고 우리가 상상 할 수 있는
watching these results is that well if
또 다른 아이디어는 만약 우리가 하나의
we don't need demonstrations to be
특정한 작업에서 성공하기 위해 데모가 필요하지 않다면
at a single specific task but we can
잘 해낼 수 있다는 것입니다 but we can
instead use demonstrations for a wide
그러나 우리는 대신 이 조건화된 트릭으로
range of different tasks
광범위한 다른 작업에
with this conditioning trick do we even
데모를 사용할 수 있습니다.
need them to be demonstrations at all
우리에게 그것들이 데모가 될 필요가 있을까요?
could we instead maybe get bad random
대신에 우리는 나쁜상태의
and use that random data as
무작위 데이터를가지고 그 무작위 데이터를
demonstrations so basically
시연으로 사용할 수 있을까요?
if you have a bad trajectory but that
만약 당신이 나쁜 궤젹을 가지고 있더라도
trajectory reaches some state maybe it's
그 궤적이 어떤 상태에 도달한다면
actually a good trajectory
어떤 상태에 도달 했든 간에
for whatever state it reached and that's
그것은 실제로 좋은 궤적일 것입니다.
actually the algorithm described in this
그리고 그것이 이 논문에 설명된 알고리즘이며
paper called learning to reach goals
해당 알고리즘은 반복된 supervised learning(지도학습)을 통해
by iterating supervised learning where
목표에 도달하는 학습입니다.
the overall recipe
여기서 전체적인 레시피는
is to actually start from scratch
처음부터 시작하는 것입니다.
there's no human data at all
사람이 제공한 데이터는 전혀 없습니다
instead we start with a random policy
대신 무작위 정책으로 시작합니다
that random policy collects random data
랜덤 정책(policy)이 랜덤 데이터를 수집하지만
but then that random data is relabeled
랜덤 데이터가 도달한 목표에 따라
with whatever goal that it reached so if
다시 학습되므로
your random trajectory reached
랜덤 궤적이 s_t 상태에
state st then it's a good demonstration
도달했다면 목표 s_t에 대한 좋은 시연입니다.
st that is then used to
그리고 나서 무작위보다
retrain the policy
더 나은 목표에 도달하기 위한
which gives you a better policy for
더 나은 정책을 제공하는
reaching goals that is better than
정책을 재교육하는 데
random and then you repeat
사용됩니다
and it can actually be shown that
이 과정을 반복하면
repeating this process can actually
내부 루프 모방 학습 절차와
solve some pretty sophisticated
이 라벨링 단계 만으로
reinforcement learning tasks
상당히 복잡한 강화 학습 과제를
just with an inner loop imitation
해결할 수 있다는 것을
learning procedure and this relabeling stage
알 수 있습니다.